[Music]
thank you
hello good evening good day everybody
wherever you are in the world and
welcome to the ask a visit Show episode
156 I hope you're all doing very well
as always let's see who all is there on
the live chat with us let's see who all
is there I can see pritamely
TDC Rahul Soviet Union with Akash subham
The aquan Vault gaming Sangeeta shots
foreign
son
and lots and lots and lots and lots of
other people thank you so much all of
you for being on the live stream I
really appreciate it thank you very much
I won't be able to greet you all
individually but thank you I really
appreciate it
right let us now begin but before I
begin
uh let me remind those of you who are
not aware that uh this podcast the ask
show and the other podcasts are
available on Spotify and apple let me
put it on the screen in case you all are
not aware of this the ask Abhijit show
is available on Spotify all or Spotify
all the episodes are there
the Indian interest podcast is also
entirely available on Spotify so is the
ability podcast with various people who
I speak to and these podcasts are also
available on Apple podcasts and and also
on Google podcasts and wherever else
podcasts are available so in case this
is something that you prefer to do
listen to podcasts instead of view
viewing them you can certainly do that
on Apple on Spotify on Google podcasts
and everywhere else podcasts are
available so just a quick reminder to
those of you who may not be aware the
links are always in the in the uh
description of the video of every video
but just in case people don't look let
me remind them all about this yeah
and also before I begin I would like to
I should have done this a long time ago
but I would like to thank Rama Lakshmi
for uh for religiously putting the
timestamps at the end of every report at
the end of every live stream very
quickly Rama Lakshmi puts the timestamps
with all the you know time codes of all
the questions that answer also on the
other podcast the Indian interest
podcast so Rama Lakshmi thank you very
much I don't know who you are where you
live and all but you have been doing
this for such a long time and I am very
grateful and I thank you very much from
the bottom of my heart for doing this
because it really helps everybody else
it helps the viewers who want to you
know dial down to a specific question
and see the answer to that so this this
uh
this YouTube channel is extremely
Community Driven isn't it lots of people
have been doing this in the past in the
past I remember harshit 2.0 used to do
the the timestamps for a long time the
summer also has been doing it from time
to time in the past initially it was
Akash bowler who was doing the
timestamps so I've been so fortunate
that so many wonderful people have been
helping the community out in this manner
so thank you to all of you who have been
doing this in the past and especially
thank you Rama Lakshmi please put this
in your timestamps
um
excuse me I'm I'm recovering from some
what seems to be some kind of virus yeah
viruses are doing the rounds these days
anyway I'm good I'm good all right let's
get into the questions now what
questions do we have
uh let's go to question number one
Sharma is Big says do you did you talk
about history geopolitics and science
with girls when you were younger if I
discuss subjects that are considered to
be nerdy wanted make me seem to be a bit
geeky so how should I go about this how
should I effectively incorporate these
ideas into my game for maximum
excuse me results
my dad did not teach me these skills Etc
thank well yeah so listen did I ever
speak about geopolitics and science and
history with girls I don't think so I
don't think I ever did that it's not
about talking about this too with girls
or boys typically most people have no
interest in these things
most people they gossip a lot and the
topic of their gossip it just eludes me
what they talk about and what they can
talk about all day all that they just
keep on gossiping I I typically don't
gossip I don't understand what gossip is
about I don't understand how people do
small talks a small talk is something I
don't understand I can talk about issues
I can talk about things so you know I
always found throughout my life that
history geopolitics science these topics
most 99 of people have no interest in in
these in these things especially in
daily life
when I do these these live streams
people watch and clearly people want to
understand this but in daily life when
the most people have no interest in this
um and also it's it's you know girls are
wired kind of differently and boys are
wired differently girls are are they
have their interests are in specific
topics and typically boys are interested
in other topics people may tell you
these days that you know all everybody
is equal of course everybody should have
equal rights and equal everything
opportunities but the genders are wired
differently mentally so boys are more
outdoorsy types and they are more
interested in sports and action movies
and things like that and girls are more
into other stuff
uh so
I typically did not ever discuss these
things with girls or even with most boys
maybe a couple of boys when I was a kid
a teenager and all that
um now about the game and all that
listen I was a big time nerd as a kid
I I had glasses I still do have glasses
for you know for looking far away uh so
I had glasses and I was interested in
all the geekiest subjects in the world
you know Mathematics and Science History
all those things so yes I was a nerd the
thing that prevented me from being a
nerd entirely is that I was extremely
interested in sports and physical
activities and I am a very large
imposing you know solidly built person
so uh
well that that kind of took me out of
the nerd Zone and into whatever other
Zone there is yeah so I was interested I
had a lot of interests uh now the thing
is that if you discuss certain topics
you look like a nerd if you discuss
other topics you look like something
else you know you got to be who you are
you've got to be who you are I was a
nerd and I kind of embraced it as a kid
what and I also was interested in sports
it's not because I I did not develop any
interest in sports to escape being a
nerd it's just that I actually liked
Sports
you know and if I had the opportunity if
I had had the opportunity I would have
liked to indulge in that a bit a lot
more than I did so um you got to be who
you are I'm not sure about game or
something I never thought of uh my game
or any such thing when when you talk
about a game your game it's typically
about impressing the opposite sex isn't
it that's what it is about I think
you've got to be who you are you got to
be the best version of yourself
uh so uh and of course you've got to
develop yourself physically you cannot
simply study study study and not do
anything else you have to be a
well-rounded person you've got to well
study you've got to have knowledge you
got to have a good career you also got
to develop yourself physically you've
got to have interests outside of your
field of study and and career all those
things so overall if you are a
well-rounded individual well-rounded
human being then I suppose your game
will be good so that's what I could tell
you uh typically I in my personal
experience I have never found people in
real life in day to day life who have
much of an interest in geopolitics or
science and typically is especially in
school as a teenager in college not so
much in University but at until the
college level if you talk about these
things people look at you like who is
this what is the person talking about
what weird interests does this person
have that's typically how it is of
course once you go into University where
things are more specialized and people
are more serious about about higher
studies uh then attitudes change and
when you go to the higher studies level
especially at the University level then
people value specific domains of
knowledge and all that so that's how it
typically is but in your day-to-day life
these uh
these topics uh don't hold much currency
because most people don't know what they
are and what is what they're about and
they will be weirded out that why is
this person discussing these weird
things does it think it's an expert of
some kind you know that's how it is so
that's what I can tell you if you want
to
uh what does it develop your game
incorporate ideas into your game you got
to be the best version of yourself which
means raise your standards
in in in an all-round manner that's what
I can say about this
okay swapnil says what is your Take On
The Rise of AI applications like chat
GPT what's your projection of AI in the
future should we trust chat GPD for
answers more than you know me they'll
always trust and support you no matter
what thank you so much swapnil I really
appreciate it
um what's my take on AI applications
look AI is a set of algorithms you you
have a machine learning algorithm that
goes through a whole bunch of data an
enormous amount of data it may be
textual data it may be image based based
data image based data it could be video
files audio files whatever so you have a
bunch of algorithms for text you have a
bunch of algorithms for uh for video for
audio uh for images all that and you
train your your uh AI which is the the
neural network essentially uh
based on the text or whatever data
you're feeding it and you train it for a
certain amount of time and then it
starts picking up patterns and pattern
recognition and then it can give you
results now you can always tweak the
algorithms to make them more effective
or to introduce censorship and bias into
them
so any AI system application like chat
GPT or or Bing AI or or whatever it is
it's gonna have a set of inbuilt biases
please understand this and of course it
will not have all the information in the
world it won't have all the knowledge in
the world it won't have trawled through
all the information that's available on
the internet there will be specific
pieces of data or information or books
or whatever it is that it may not be
aware of and you typically find that
when you ask questions about AI you can
kind of get a sense of whether it
understands the topic deeply or not and
often you find especially if you are an
expert in a certain domain that AI often
not often but sometimes makes up answers
it sometimes makes up answers and it
gives you fictitious information some
people call it AI hallucinating or
whatever it's not hallucinating you ask
a question and AI it seems to feel that
it has to give you some kind of answer
um you'll find that more I think with
being these days I I personally haven't
tested the AI hallucination part so my
point is that you cannot trust AI
entirely
you cannot trust chat jpd for answers
entirely you can certainly use that to
get a bunch of information that
otherwise would take you many hours to
discover but then you have to do your
own due diligence and cross verify every
single piece of information it is
spitting out at you that's what you have
to do so it can you know if you if you
are a professor or whatever it can AI
like chat GPD or Bingo whatever can
serve as a kind of unpaid research
assistant for you if you're a professor
if you are in some other field if you're
a student also right it can help you
with
you know feed you a lot of information
that otherwise would take you hours to
discover but then you have to do your
diligence due diligence and cross verify
cross check every piece of information
because it is not necessarily going to
be 100 correct
and sometimes it may it may look like
it's giving you opinions instead of data
or or factual information so you got to
may do your due diligence you have to
know how to cross check information
that's a skill everybody has to develop
especially those of you who are now
beginning to you know use chat jpd or
whatever else
uh to obtain information do research do
studies whatever it is so uh in the
future see we are just in the infancy of
these chat bots in these AI systems they
are now able to talk just like a human
being it certainly does pass the Turing
test you can't tell if it's a person or
a machine on the other side of the
screen that's interacting with you so
it's definitely passed the during test
but it's not
conscious it's not awake it's not
self-aware
you ask it questions about
self-awareness it's going to talk talk
back to you as if it's a human being and
all that but it's it's just a machine uh
it is generating uh text based on
probabilistic uh on a probabilistic
approach that's what it is doing uh so
we are simply in the infancy right now
of AI a year from now you're gonna have
much more systems that are way more
powerful than what we have today chart
jbd and being AI just a year from now in
five years time the whole world is going
to be totally different the world will
have changed completely so AI is gonna
be the future but people who blindly
trust AI are going to be led down the
Garden Path please understand that you
blindly trust Ai and and you know
believe whatever it says you're gonna
it's gonna be just like studying your
ncert textbooks and believing everything
blindly
that's what most people do unfortunately
I would say 98 99 of students students
simply believe everything your history
textbooks in your history teachers teach
you
you do and they're gonna go ahead and do
the same with AI
so this is for those of you who watch
the channel you the the those of you who
watch the channel are not like that you
you actually do understand that things
uh you know these things cannot be
trusted entirely ncrd textbooks Indian
history textbooks professors uh experts
historians they they are very
problematic aren't they we know that so
so think of AI just the same way as you
would think of Irfan Habib or romila
that's how you think of AI so do study
pramila's textbooks because there will
be an information that will be relevant
and useful but she's gonna inject a
whole bunch of opinion and buyers into
it into the information so as long as
you're aware
that this book is gonna contain a lot of
bias and opinion rather than facts once
you as long as you're aware of it you
can study it and and as long as you do
your due diligence and cross verify
everything you'll be fine otherwise
you're gonna be led down the garden to
Garden Path and be taken for a fool so
the same thing the same approach has to
be there with AI cross check everything
it says so ideally what you would want
to do if you want to learn something new
or gain some information about let's say
the Mongol invasion of Carpathia or
whatever it was then ask AI to give you
a bunch of 20 points explain the
so-and-so event and give me in 20 bullet
points and then take each bullet point
and cross verify the information from
wherever you can other obtain
information from reliable sources
that's what you need to do in the future
AI is going to take over everything
right now we're just having this chat
Bots you know a chat uh chat box that
chat back to you in the future I think
it's already there AI is now able to
generate music totally unique music
interesting music some sometimes it's
gonna it's already able to generate
images and artwork you enter a text
prompt it's gonna throw out spit out an
image at you so AI is already generating
images AI has already gone into the you
know entered the realm of Music
generation
all you have to do is you tell it what
genre you want whether it is electronic
music whether it is classical music or
whether it is hip hop or whatever the
genres are and you can enter the beats
per minute BPM musicians will understand
that and then you can you know add some
other parameters you know whatever they
are and it's gonna give you like five or
ten or as many as you want tracks based
on the parameters so music is there
images are there text is already there
in the future you're gonna have video
and very realistic video so it's gonna
create this problem of deep fakes you
know people are gonna superimpose
somebody's face on in an AI video and
it'll look like it's that person and
even the voice can be replicated
so you're gonna have all these you know
videos and all these things that will
come up
um so it's gonna totally change lots of
Industries it's gonna disrupt a lot of
Industries it's already disrupting art
you know you you can get AI you produce
any amount of artwork in the style of
any artist
let's say you want a dog eating a
sandwich on a beach on Mars in the style
of Vincent Van Gogh it's gonna do it for
you in a few matter of seconds it's
gonna speed out 20 images like that in a
matter of seconds imagine any weird
thing you want in the style of EX
artists or why artists or Z artist it's
gonna do it for you it's already putting
artists out of work
it's going to do the same thing for
musicians right now all music you know
in the 21st century all music sounds the
same already the big music labels they
are they they have done that to music
there is no individuality music anymore
the lyrics not make any sense I mean the
lyrics are all the same the music is all
the same blah blah blah nonsense so very
soon AI is going to produce these music
tracks and musicians and singers are
going to be put out of commission that's
what what's going to happen the
education industry is going to be
totally disrupted so there's a huge
disruption coming and people with very
specific skills will be able to survive
this
especially when AI comes into the field
of Robotics when robotics when robots
will be equipped with AI they're going
to take over entire industries that are
that are based on low skilled labor
foreign give me let me give you an
example of high skill labor in which
robotics is going to deserve the world
fighter jets
fighter aircraft today you spend
hundreds of man hours training fighter
pilots
in a very specific set of skills very
very difficult to master set of skills
in the next five to ten years this field
is going to be entirely taken over by
robotics robotic aircraft
equipped with AI systems so these
robotic aircraft are going to take over
the role of fighter pilots
and they So you you're gonna take the
pages for instance the pages fight a
plane
equip it with AI which operates
autonomously
and then you don't have a need a pilot
on that that's what's going to happen
very soon
another aircraft so it's going to
disrupt the entire world and we're gonna
have to figure out how to survive this
it's going to take our jobs especially
low skilled jobs low skilled labor it's
going to be totally made redundant
so people are gonna have to governments
are going to have to find a solution to
this and we individuals will have to
find a solution to this we if you want
to remain relevant in the world you have
to acquire a set of skills develop a set
of skills invest in yourself in such a
way that it's something that AI can't
take over
so that's the conundrum we are all
facing and maybe I need to you know
maybe do an entire episode on this and
think about it deeply and give you
specific answers of how to do that but
thus as of today as of right now like
this is what I can tell you prepare for
what's coming it's coming and no one's
gonna stop it it's this is just the
beginning we are in the infancy of AI
2023 is the year of AI it's the infancy
of AI by 25 the world is going to be
totally different by 2030 well I don't
even know what to say so it's coming
prepare for it
it's going to affect every one of us
each one of us
okay another question by swapnel can you
explain goodles incompleteness theorem
and its implications on artificial
intelligence excellent question so let's
first talk about who was Kurt godell
shall we let us type in Godel
go Dell and let me put that on the
screen just give me a second he was an
Austrian mathematician that's who Kurt
Godel was let's put him on the screen
let's see what it looks like looked like
uh
it was an austrian-born logistician
mathematician and philosopher he was
born in 1906 died in 1978 so that's what
it looked like now what is godel's
incompleteness theorem and how do I
explain it in a non-technical
non-mathematical sense imagine you have
an enormous puzzle
you know imagine you have huge jigsaw
puzzle with hundreds maybe thousands of
pieces
and your job is to put the puzzle
together
so you work really hard you may take
days or weeks putting all the pieces
together with a lot of frustration lot
of hard work and finally when you think
you've solved the puzzle you realize
that a few pieces are missing they were
missing from the beginning but you
didn't know about it
so Google's incompleteness theorem is
kind of like that it says that in
mathematics there are some things that
you simply cannot prove or solve no
matter how hard you try it's like in
mathematics there are some missing
pieces that you simply can't find that
is in in a very rudimentary form what
dollars uh incompleteness here means so
it's a landmark result in mathematical
logic that which I think he he proved it
in 1929 1930 somewhere around there and
it totally uh totally radically altered
our understanding of the limits of
mathematical understanding so it says
any formal system of mathematics which
is sufficiently complex and powerful
enough to express arithmetic contains
statements within itself that cannot be
proven or disproven within the system
itself so it which what it means is that
there are some true mathematical
statements that are unprovable using the
rules and axioms of the system
so this is when it came out it shocked
people it shocked mathematicians because
it challenges the idea that mathematics
is a self-contained completely
self-contained closed system that can in
principle provide a complete and
consistent account of all mathematical
truths
so that's why it was shocking now why is
it important for the field of AI
so you know what in what is an AI system
so it has a lot of this incompleteness
theorem has several implications for the
field of artificial intelligence
the most important thing is that it
places fundamental limits on what can be
accomplished by an AI system an
automated reasoning system what is an AI
system it's an automated reasoning
system that's what it is it's a bunch of
algorithms automated reasoning automated
reasoning is mathematical in nature so
Google's incompleteness theorem places
fundamental results on what can
fundamental limits on what can be
accomplished by an automated reasoning
system so any AI that uh any AI system
that relies on automated reasoning
which is all AI systems these systems
will always have some limitations and
they will not be able to fully replicate
the capabilities of human reasoning so
one of the goals of AI research is to
achieve strong artificial intelligence
okay let's let's remove Mr Google from
the screen here we are so one of the
goals one of the major goals of AI
research currently is to achieve strong
artificial intelligence which means
human level General AI General
artificial intelligence currently what
we have is we have AIS like the chat box
chat box that we just discussed like uh
stable diffusion and whatever else we
have which generates images and all that
so currently we have ai
which is a bunch of algorithms in what's
called Turing machines which are
consistent
axiomatic systems these are all subject
to
the theorem godel's incompleteness
theorem so this tells you
that human consciousness
transcends these algorithmic systems
these Turing machines because human
Minds through in introspection can
recognize their own inconsistencies we
do understand once you know
when we introspect we do recognize our
flaws and our inconsistencies within
ourselves in our minds
but under godels incompleteness theorem
this is impossible for Turing machines
yeah so that's why people like Roger
Penrose and and Dr swashtak also have
spoken about this they have said that
it's impossible for AI to reproduce the
real traits
of human Minds such as mathematical
Insight so even when a human being is is
you know solving mathematical problems
we are we are able to understand that
this system will have inconsistencies we
know goldils and complete this theorem
and all that so the human mind
transcends
uh
the the goals incompleteness theorem but
these algorithmic systems there's these
these Turing machines cannot they are
bound by it they are confined by it so
essentially strong AI systems want to be
able to really think because they are
limited by this incompleteness theorem
human thinking is not limited by the by
the uh
but the incompleteness theorem human
beings are illogical at times we are
irrational at times our thinking is not
mathematical our thinking our thinking
is whole wholly different we can't even
totally properly uh
properly Define the the process of human
thought or or no create a flowchart or
whatever it is there are leaps of
imagination and logic you know so this
theorem essentially suggests that human
intuition and creativity play a crucial
role in mathematical reasoning
you know mathematical reasoning when we
are solving you know when we are working
on mathematics we are trying to solve a
theorem now that human Intuition or
intuition and creativity play a crucial
role in that that's the what the best
mathematicians have always been like a
people such as uh for Newman like uh
what's his name
beautiful mind I forget his name John
Nash and so on these guys were extremely
intuitive
their system of thinking was something
they could not replicate think about
ramanujan he used to say that he saw
dreams
in the night his goddess goddess would
come to him in the night in his dream
and give him mathematical theorems he
would wake up and write them down and
these these results were correct
that is incredible leaps of creativity
and intuition and who knows what else
so the human mind doesn't work like a
machine
theorem tells you that human intuition
and creativity
is something that
these Turing machines these algorithmic
machines these AI systems are incapable
of
these qualities cannot be fully
replicated in any of these systems
so this also kind of suggests that uh
there could be alternative approaches to
artificial intelligence that rely Less
on formal reasoning and maybe other
kinds of intelligence such as pattern
recognition or heuristic reasoning or or
we don't know quite yet what it is so
that's what
go deals incompleteness theorem tells us
that AI most likely will not be able to
replicate human level intelligence and
will definitely not be able to become
conscious unless we try radically
different approaches the kind of
approaches we have never tried thus far
that is what Google's incompleteness
theorem uh that's what the implications
are for the field of artificial
intelligence very interesting field I'm
just scratching the surface over here
but it's a fascinating Topic in case any
of you are interested
okay this is a question from LinkedIn I
think sujay says is a war between India
and China inevitable within this decade
interesting question is a war between
India and China inevitable
let's say the Chinese portion push India
into a war see India is not a
warmongering country India just wants
peace and Tranquility on the northern
border with Tibet India has no Ambitions
to invade Tibet and and grab Tibet and
an exhibit India has never wanted to do
that in the past 10 000 years of Indian
history we have never done that
oil more or less all right so we have
never done that and we have no Ambitions
of of making Tibet part of India so the
Chinese no the Chinese know that they
don't face any threat from India in the
Himalayas Tibet is is a region that
doesn't face any threat from from India
there is no imminent danger of an Indian
Invasion and take over of Tibet the
Chinese know that and yet the entire
border map
we must have the map
we cannot talk without Maps because maps
are very important where is the map
where is the map
right let's take a look at a look at the
border this is the map
and uh the India Tibet border is
essentially a very very long border that
stretches from uh Kashmir jamun Kashmir
the Afghan border all the way to
arunachal Pradesh and the Burmese border
the makma
but my headline
so the Chinese know that India is not a
nation that is threatening an invasion
of Tibet India has never done that Well
India have the chance if it wanted in
the 1950s India did not ever bother to
do that so India is not going to do that
and yet the border is highly militarized
it is because of the Chinese threat to
India that the border is militarized not
because of the Indian threat to China
the Chinese no they know very well that
India doesn't pose a threat
now the question is is a war inevitable
it is it is gonna have what is going to
happen only if the Chinese make the move
only the Chinese trigger off you know
their actions trigger a war or they
cross a certain red line that India
cannot uh you know help but retaliate to
only in that case will a war happen so
the question really is that does China
want to go with him to war with India
within this decade
so let's understand uh the logic is
China in a position where it can afford
to go to war with India what does it
stand to gain what does it stand to lose
it may stand to gain a little bit of
territory if they think they can win
some territory from India they may want
to cut off the the Siliguri Corridor
which uh you know this little uh piece
of geography over here
uh they may want to perhaps possibly
take some part of our own natural
position maybe the entirety foreign
if they think they can win a war then
they may stand to take some make some
more territorial gains from their
perspective from their point of view
from their thinking that's what they
could gain from a war but then what will
happen that will push India entirely
into the American embrace
in America I'll be very happy with that
so it does right now India is following
a really genuinely independent foreign
policy India is not overtly in the U.S
Camp the only reason why India is part
of the quad and all that is because of
the Chinese threat and that is entirely
up to China whether they want to keep
this happening or not
so uh so if China goes to war with India
they
are guaranteed to push India 100 into
the American camp
and that is going to be Advantage U.S
and the US is the only superpower in the
world way more powerful than China the
Chinese are you know they are not even
able to take back Taiwan they are not
able to break free of the first or the
second or the third island chain the
Americans are the major power in the
Asia Pacific region not China despite
whatever you may believe
so the Chinese are you know it would be
extremely
counterproductive for the Chinese
to go to what to to make a bigger enemy
of India than what they've already done
right now India is trying to to pursue a
balanced and entirely independent
foreign policy that is something that's
in China's interest and the thing is
that the Chinese rise is no longer
happening the so-called peaceful rise of
China until 2019 that's what was
happening the Chinese were on track to
replace and displace the U.S U.S as the
world's biggest economy by 2035 to 2040
or thereabouts definitely by 2050 that
was a big ambition the big aim of China
that's no longer going to happen the
Chinese economy is not projected to
surpass the U.S or equal the U.S economy
until 2067 if ever at all most likely it
will never happen the Chinese economy
and the GDP is Contracting
most Nations don't trust China anymore
the belt and Road initiative is is dead
in the water the maritime still growth
is not happening no real progress
anymore these were the Great vehicles
that were supposed to make China
superpower it's not happening and
there's an impending demographic
disaster in China the population
collapse is coming it's already
happening now the total 40 literate is
less than 1.2 which is a which is a
genuine catastrophe for Any Nation
and the population is predicted to
become half of what it is by 2100 and
most of the population by the time will
be elderly that's a disaster is a nation
that faces this sort of prospect
in any kind of position to make a huge
enemy of India which for in for India
the demographic window is going to be
open until 2040 2050. so India has a
demographic dividend China is staring at
a demographic disaster China's economy
is Contracting India's economy is rising
China is you know from if they think
logically and rationally and calmly and
unemotionally like the Chinese do they
will realize they are in no position to
make a bigger enemy of India than what
they have already done
over the past 60 70 years so I think
that it is now unlikely
that the Chinese will want to go to war
with India this decade and by the time
this decade is out India is going to be
a much larger economy the way things are
going so after in the 2030s it will be
even less likely that the Chinese would
want to tangle with India in any sense
whatsoever
uh and the Chinese are already making
the noises you know the right noises the
the new Chinese foreign minister was in
India this past week he met with Dr Jai
Shankar and you know the Chinese the the
the statements they made where that they
want a normalization of the Border
situation and you know
whatever making the Border situation
less dense and bringing the things back
to normalcy and it appears that things
may be a foot on the ground as well in
the direction the Chinese are trying to
de-escalate now that's what they want
they understand the long-term prospects
that they are facing and they understand
the kind of growth India will most
likely have and the Chinese are in no
position to actually defeat India in the
Himalayan war in in extremely
challenging
Terrain
like the Himalayas especially with the
climate the Chinese have significant
disadvantages they may try if they do
try to fight a war with India they may
it may be extraordinary
counterproductive for them they may
actually lose the war and lose face very
badly
India could take out lots of their bases
in Tibet the bases in Tibet are naked to
the to the open eye they are very well
they're properly visible from satellite
images and everything and they cannot be
hidden
on the other hand in India we can hide
things because we have in the enormous
Forest cover in the arunachal in
Northern India Etc and the when it comes
to extremely high altitude Warfare
technology takes a backseat in the
quality of your soldiers takes a front
seat and then also India has a
significant Advantage so the Chinese are
not in a position to win a Himalayan war
with India this time the Indian army is
waiting for the Chinese to make a move
if they go if they cross a line they're
going to be taught a lesson they will
never ever forget and in China in China
in the Chinese Communist Party failure
is never tolerated if Xi Jinping tries
to fight with the war with India and
suffers a setback it's going to be the
end of his political career maybe his
life
so I think
two years ago I would have told you only
something else because at that time the
Chinese economy was booming
but in the past two two and a half three
years everything is made at 360 180
degree turn at you a u-turn
and now things are very different for
China so I don't think China is in any
position to to tangle with India and
start a war with India this decade or in
the next two decades or maybe not this
Century now that's what I think
so I think a war between India and China
is not inevitable this decade I think it
is more and it's becoming more and more
unlikely now that's how rapidly the
global geopolitical scenario has changed
and turned around two years ago it was
totally different now is totally
different so I think it's Advantage
India India has to focus on the economy
economic growth development uh reforms
uh infrastructure
and the military growth if India does
this I think nobody except the U.S can
stop India then
s s a n says why is the world listening
to India now and not ever before what
have we done that we are in a position
in this position now and what mistakes
to avoid so that the young population
helps in the growth of the country uh
why is the yes the world is listening to
India now though in India figures in
most Global conversations uh great power
conversations and what's what have we
done now that we did not do before
well firstly we have a very
strong independent foreign policy which
prioritizes India's national interest
over everything else over everything
else we don't care about the Americans
want we don't care what the Chinese want
what the Russians want we care what we
what is in our best interest and we will
always put that first and that's how we
are dealing with international relations
when you do that people respect you
when you have self-respect people
respect you in the past India the The
Stance of the Indian government in the
in the former prime ministers was that
India has no ambition of being a great
power we we have no Ambitions of being
great
and our foreign policy was oftentimes I
would say uh it would take a backseat to
the to the National priorities of other
nations that's how it was always done in
the past it's the first time since 1947
India has a robust
independent foreign policy that always
puts India's national interests first so
that's the first thing and secondly
India's economy is growing again
it's stagnated for a long time but it's
now growing again and it's projected to
keep growing and India is focusing on
infrastructure development which is
going to speed up the economy so you
India is building 30 40 50 kilometers of
Highways every single day imagine that
we are bringing in hundreds of new
high-tech trains the one day about the
trains and we're gonna have soon in the
next five ten years maybe start building
more bullet trains we are building new
airports almost every year a few new
airports come in we are significantly
expanding our Airline Fleet the number
of airports that we have entire two Tire
three cities are also going to become
connected by air it's now affordable for
just about anybody to travel by air in
the past it was like a big luxury for
someone to crawl by air so everything is
changing now the data rates are
extremely low in India the internet data
rates lowest in the world I think
India is totally transforming and
revolutionizing uh the entire
infrastructure that we have that's what
this government is doing uh it's these
things have never done before the entire
country is more or less electrified
obviously there'll be some spots
somewhere or the other where the
electricity has not reached yet because
we have an extremely challenging Terrain
in some parts of India but
more or less the entire country is now
electrified you can see the results from
space now in light Time images we we are
you know if you look at the nighttime
imagery of nations in the kind of light
output is there India surpasses China
already by a big margin
if you if you consider that as a
yardstick and um
so there's so and everybody has bank
accounts now everybody has Insurance
these things they are gonna bear fruit
in the next 10 20 30 years
you you will not see the result
immediately but it's it's already
put India on the cusp of a major
economic explosion
productivity
and and growth of the economy that's
what's happening the world sees it
they can't help but see it and when you
do this the world will take you
extremely seriously you place an order
for 800 aircraft but roughly it's gonna
create a million jobs in the US and many
more in in France in France and the UK
we are able to now affect the world's
economy
through our own actions that solve our
interests
in when you put yourself when you do the
really hard work and you put yourself in
this position the world will listen to
you the world will take you extremely
seriously and they will respect you so
that is what India has done it has been
done by the government of Narendra Modi
nobody else
although that is the fact that is a fact
no one else did it Mr Manmohan Singh did
nothing of this sort
uh neither did the prime ministers who
came before Mr Manmohan Singh doctor
sorry so so that's what's happened in
India has never been taken seriously in
the past only in the last five six years
this has happened and now they are
taking India very seriously
and it's going to only increase in the
future
India is where China was in the 1990s
right now that's where we are the
Chinese were extremely serious about
their growth about their National
interest and the world started taking
them seriously in the 1990s itself
they already said they had started
talking about China as a potential
superpower in the 1990s itself
India is now at that stage they Now
understand India is serious India means
business India is not going to tolerate
any nonsense
and that's why they are taking India
seriously now
in the next five or ten years they will
they will most likely take India more
seriously than they take China right now
it's a possibility if we do things right
so that's why this change has come about
it's come about because of the policies
of the Narendra Modi government
and the incredible hard work they've
done you may like him or hate him I
don't care what it is facts are facts
uh now what mistakes to avoid so that
the young population helps in the growth
of the country well the mistake you
avoid is you don't stop reforming the
nation reforming the government
governance system reforming the
bureaucracy reforming everything and you
don't stop creating more infrastructure
we are just beginning we have to we have
to connect the entire nation thoroughly
through highways through railroads
through airports we have to reform the
bureaucracy we have to reform the
Judiciary we have to reform the
governance system we have to root out
corruption which is still a big issue we
have to reform the the political system
uh maybe bring in a new constitution a
new uh maybe a presidential system these
are long-term goals maybe next 10 to 20
years not immediately but these things
will
truly catapult India to a genuine uh
maybe possibly even super power status
in the long run so these things need to
happen the education system needs to be
reformed there are enormous challenges
that need to be addressed but these will
happen organically as India's economic
might and Military might grows once you
do that there will be the larger is your
economy the more powerful is your
economy and Military the less foreign
interference there will there be in your
internal matters right now there is
still a significant amount of foreign
interference in our internal matters all
the millions of ngos in India many of
them are funded from abroad there are
all kinds of activities that are
happening within India many of India's
well some of India's possibly allegedly
institutions may be compromised some
would say so all these things will be
dealt with organically as India's
military and economic might grows once
you are that powerful the world will not
be in a position to interfere that much
under the name of Human Rights or
democracy or promoting this or that or
whatever it's none of your business get
out of here that's going to be the uh
message that we will give to them
eventually so that's what the government
needs to keep doing what can the young
population do to grow to help grow the
country well be productive
understand yourself understand what your
strengths and weaknesses are focus in
your strengths develop them more and be
productive if you are if you if you take
a nine to nine to five job do your best
in contributing to your company or to
your employer if you take up
entrepreneurship create more jobs create
more jobs and create value that the
society can actually benefit from that's
a simple thing
so raise your standards develop yourself
into a all-round uh well developed
person who has reached who can reach the
full extent of your potential and
contribute to society in whatever way
you can if everybody does that it's
going to really transform Society right
now India unfortunately is to a large
extent a nation of very low low
standards
attitude right that's what they say
so that needs to go so so the main thing
you can do is to be is to raise your
standards contribute more to society
through whatever means you have and if
you are into business or
entrepreneurship create jobs create jobs
and give new more people the opportunity
to contribute in their own way to the
nation to the society that's what you
can do
says Japanese foreign minister has
skipped the G24 Minister Summit in India
the Japanese government stated that it
happened due to budget session in the
parliament of Japan the US's Bloomberg
media described it as Japan snub to
India in recent Times India Japan joined
military exercises and bilateral
cooperation has taken place then what's
your view on this U.S for sale State's
decision is it a matter of concern or
not well you know
understand the chronology chronology
like they would say
you first had the G20 foreign minister
Summit and right after that you had the
quad Summit
in the same week in the same week
the for the G20 foreign minister Summit
uh the foreign minister of Japan does
not come
and right after that
the same week you have the quad foreign
Minister's Summit which happens in New
Delhi itself
in the formulas of Japan does come for
that
so I would say it's not a snub to India
that he he decided to skip the G20 for
Mrs Summit it's a snub to the G20
organization that's what it is
he did not come for the G20 thing he
came for the quad thing in New Delhi
itself right after the G20 Summit ended
in the same week itself so in what way
is it a snubbed to India it simply means
that for the for the government of Japan
G20 does not figure high on the
priorities but the quad does the quad is
extremely important for them it tells
you what the government's priorities are
both events happen in India both events
happen in the same week and he came to
India
he came to New Delhi he met with Dr Jai
Shankar he met with the other foreign
ministers the quad Summit the quad
foreign minister Summit the event took
place
it went off perfectly fine so if the U.S
Bloomberg media has described it as
Japan's nub to India they need to stop
smoking whatever they're smoking
yeah
India and Japan we understand Japan is a
u.sal state like like I I've started
using the terminology I'm sure it's
spread now
um
Japan as we know is under U.S military
occupation it's been that way since 1945
their foreign policy essentially is an
extension of U.S foreign policy uh so
that tells you that for the U.S Japan
needs to take the quad seriously they
want to use Japan as an integral and
strong component of the quad and for the
for the U.S Japan need not attend the
G20 Summit because the G20 is is well
it's a different cattle of fish the G20
has historically been uh an organization
that uh prioritizes in Focus
prioritizes Economic Development and
growth and cooperation
that's historically what it what it's
been about
these days they are introducing more
geopolitical activities they're using it
as as a tool for as an extension as a
tool for uh for prioritizing and
promoting their geopolitical interests
that we that's what we saw in New Delhi
this time it was a very politicized
uh Summit
and uh the foreign ministers were not
able to come to a consensus about the
final draft document the final document
that that is put out which is why which
is why the text reflected that that
there was there was a lack of unanimity
unanimity about the various paragraphs
all the information don't agree to
paragraphs three and four in the
document so that's what happened um
so now it's been being politicized but
overall it's in in no
in no sense a snub to India if it is a
stub it's a snob to the G20 group of
Nations it's not a snub to India so
Japan prioritizes the quad over G20
that's all it tells you and they did
send the deputy foreign minister for the
G20 Summit so so that's that so it is
not a matter of concern for India
obviously India needs to read the tea
leaves very carefully we have to think
about see every action in in global
geopolitics every action has
significance every action has
award and covered meanings for instance
the kind of uh welcome that Mr Sergey
lavrov received in India when he reached
Delhi red carpet welcomed lots of
officials to meet him you know proper
respect given to him and his Nation
that is that contrasts very strongly
with the welcome that the German foreign
minister the lady was given I don't
remember her name uh there was no red
carpet for her and there was nobody to
welcome her except for some low ranking
officials one or two and her own uh
Embassy staff
that that is a very not so subtle
message that India has sent to Germany
that we don't take you seriously anymore
you don't matter to us
that's what India has told Germany very
clearly this time Russia really matters
to India Germany we don't dig them
seriously so so everything in
geopolitics has significance every
action has significance so Japan chose
to send their Deputy foreign minister
instead of their actual foreign minister
for the G20 Summit but for the quad
Summit they send their foreign minister
so it's not in any means by any sense a
snap to India it's simply a snub to the
G20 it's the the Japanese government is
saying that the G20 is not that
important to us but the quad is
that's all it is there's something else
to it
all right next question
says does India also have a nuclear
football or something like POTUS has
with himself
just kidding
also can the PM prime minister of India
give the direct command to fire nuclear
missiles okay what is this nuclear
Football let's take a look at nuclear
football let me put that on the screen
so the nuclear football is a briefcase
Let's uh where where are we let me put
that on the screen
nuclear football it's a briefcase that
uh always travels with the U.S president
that's typically what it looks like it's
carried by military personnel it's
that's what it looks like and this this
briefcase contains a device that has all
the nuclear launch codes it is what
enables the US president to if required
launch a nuclear strike or retaliative
strike or attack from anywhere in the
world using the contents of this
briefcase so it would have a device
which enables the president to do this
and this device is supposed to travel
with the US president everywhere he goes
it should always be in close proximity
to the U.S president because the U.S
president is the only person who has who
has the authorization to to launch or to
authorize a nuclear strike that's what
the nuclear football is
I remember an incident in I think 2017
when President Trump visited China and
uh he was supposed to go to the Great
Hall of the people or whatever it's
called in Beijing this big big Hall and
give a speech there and his uh his his
Entourage
contained I mean they had the nuclear
football with them and the Chinese were
trying to prevent them from bringing
this device into the Great Hall of the
people and there was an actual physical
altercation a scuffle between the
security Personnel of China and the US
and eventually the Chinese had to
apologize and they allowed the nuclear
football to be brought with President
Trump inside the inside the hall
so this demonstrates that this device is
supposed to always be very close to the
U.S president wherever he is when this
is something that he that goes with him
whenever he travels outside of the White
House in the white house there is a
proper command structure or whatever
from where he can launch he can
authorize a nuclear strike otherwise
this device travels with him now the
question obviously is so now that we
understand what the nuclear football is
I don't know why they call it a football
but whatever maybe that's how it shape
inside we don't know
so the question is does India also have
something like this uh does the prime
minister of India also have such a
device that that is always close in
close proximity to him
I have seen often times
uh Indian security Personnel the highest
authorization security person who are in
the immediate Entourage of the Prime
Minister of India
I have seen I have witnessed them also
at times carrying a big bulky briefcase
whenever Mr Modi goes there will be one
one gentleman very dressed very very
sharply dark suit duck glasses something
in the year device in the year and that
gentleman will be carrying a large
um briefcase
so I don't know what that is but it
looks like India may also have some such
device I mean it makes sense for India
to to for the president for the prime
minister to travel with a device like
that so that a nuclear strike can be
launched if required ever I hope it
never happens but the uh the option
always has to be there uh so as far as I
know in India it is only the Prime
Minister who can give the direct command
to launch a nuclear strike
the president of India is a ceremonial
position no real power the president
doesn't have the authorization or the or
the power to do that and neither does
any other politician it's only the Prime
Minister who can give the direct command
and then the command will be executed I
Believe by by
elements within the Indian armed forces
the actual strike
so what sort of missile to launch where
it is supposed to
to which places is it supposed to go
visit pay a visit to uh what is the
you know the the yield of the nuclear
weapon all those calibrations all those
all those things will be already
programmed into the device if it exists
um so yeah I think it is possible that
the Indian Prime Minister may also have
to be devices I don't think they have
ever answered this question or given any
statement to this effect but one does
see wherever Modi Prime Minister Modi
travels that somebody carries a
briefcase kind of kind of thing uh very
close to him I've seen that on on a
number of occasions so in the case of
the us we know they have such a device
the nuclear football India may possibly
have it uh when when President Putin of
Russia travels I I don't think I've
noticed anyone carrying them maybe they
keep it very discreet it makes a lot of
sense for Mr Putin to also travel with a
device like that because you know
when when the leader travels abroad
that's that's actually the best time to
to launch an attack on a nation
so I think possibly Russia may also have
it which are the other nations that have
nuclear weapons uh we know it's the US
Russia India we spoke about them China
has it uh China has nuclear weapons
France UK Israel North Korea and
Pakistan Pakistan is a rogue State
obviously the Pakistani prime minister I
don't think has the authority to launch
nuclear attacks it's only the Army Chief
who would have it I suppose in North
Korea I'm sure it's Mr Kim Jong-un who
has the authority to do it he rarely if
ever travels out of the country so we
don't know if he has such a device when
it comes to Israel
the prime minister of Israel does travel
a lot I'm not sure I suppose it's the
Prime Minister who should have the
authority but once again Israel is not a
self-declared nuclear State we know they
have nuclear weapons but they have never
declared it officially so we don't know
what this status is when it comes to the
UK I don't think the UK prime minister
has the launch quotes for their nuclear
missiles the UK is nothing but an
extension of the U.S especially foreign
policy military policy so I think and we
know that the UK's nuclear weapons the
British nuclear weapons are mated to
American missiles ballistic missiles so
it only makes sense that the launch
cause for those missiles will actually
be in the hands of the U.S president
rather than the UK's prime minister
so the UK is a nominal nuclear power but
I don't think the UK prime minister
actually has the power to launch a
nuclear attack when it comes to France I
am sure the French president Mr macron
would have the authority to launch a
nuclear strike but I have not seen as
far as I know
any such device travel with him and I
haven't seen such a thing travel with Mr
Xi Jinping either but I'm sure they all
have the ability to to launch a nuclear
strike if required from anywhere in the
world it makes sense for them to have
such a capability also with device that
travels with them
all right
good question yes
saurabh says excuse me saurabh says was
Ashoka a Buddhist before the Kalinga War
and why then why these
false narratives are pushed for such a
long period to demean Hinduism yeah
excuse me um so uh yes Ashok
Emperor Ashok did
start practicing both the Dharma the
precepts of both the Dharma before a few
years before he launched an invasion the
invasion of Kalinga the great Kalinga
War which was a which was a terrible
catastrophic War
so he it is known now that he did begin
to practice the precept of Buddhism what
we call Buddhism both the Dharma a few
years before the war
so yes he was a Buddhist before the
Kalinga War the the standard narrative
that is peddled in India's sister
textbooks is that he was a Hindu and
after the Kalinga War he was filled with
remorse and then he converted to
Buddhism as if there is a conversion
ceremony or something and then he became
all peaceful because of Buddhism so the
the message that is being said Ascend
sent or sold to students for Generations
in India history textbooks is that
Hinduism is a violent religion Buddhism
is the opposite of Hinduism it is a much
better thing than Hinduism Hinduism evil
Buddhism good Hinduism violent Buddhism
peaceful that's the message of
subliminal messaging that has been
used to brainwash generations of Indians
so why have our historians done this
it's to brainwash people
it's to the overall long-term objective
is to eradicate Hinduism and dharmic
religions from India
to turn India
the population of India to convert the
population of India to one of the
various abrahamic religion religions
typically it's just two of them
Christianity in Islam
and India's government has been hand in
glove with these foreign elements we
know that prime minister nehru the great
man himself Shri nehruji he was
instrumental in the total almost entire
conversion of various tribal communities
in Northeast India to Christianity
in 1900 less than one percent of the
population of the the Far East of India
Northeast of India was Christian
today the entire culture is wiped out
from places like nagaland and and
certain other states in the Northeast
the same is happening in Manipur
and it's it's a process that's that's
active right now
so they have eradicated the beautiful
indigenous culture of a large regions of
what we call Northeast India the Far
East of India uh and obviously that's
something that's also happening in other
parts of India it's happening wherever
you have what they call the adivasi
people
the tribal belts and all that that's
where it first begins and then they try
to bring it into the mainstream uh so
you know it's it's a process of of
uh artificially re-engineering the
demographics of India and various
governments state governments allegedly
Etc have been uh you know complicit in
this
so this is all
this is all aided by the Indian
education system when you put it into
when you when you brainwash children to
believe that their ancestral
religion culture is evil it makes it
very easy for them to at a later time in
life convert out of
their culture and the religion
so overall that's what it is they want
to uh
that's what the British wanted you know
the East India Company only was here in
India for trade and for plunder but
later on the missionary elements got
introduced in this and the objective of
the missionaries was to destroy Indian
culture and eradicate approved India's
culture and convert everyone to
Christianity
and obviously when the turkey
conventions happened their objective was
also to destroy eradicate violently
India's culture and convert everybody to
the religions that the Turks favored
they tried their best and they succeeded
to a certain extent that's why we have
these that's why the subcontinent was
divided along religious lines and right
now it's it's a so so the Indian
education system helps these elements
I have nothing against any religion in
any specific religion personally
my only thing is that uh
any attempt to artificially re-engineer
Society
has to be ended it has to be you know it
has to be made illegal so the Indian
education system is a great help
for all these foreign elements
when it comes for the Indian education
system uh subtly maligns Hinduism
portrait as evil violent regressive
foreign the RN Invasion Theory also
helps a lot to intellectualize that so
that you know college students can give
intellectual arguments as to why
Hinduism is evil it's a foreign religion
brought in by Invaders evil Invaders who
oppress the natives what natives
so that is the reason why all of this
exists in the Indian education system
and it all is this way because the 19th
century colonial education system that
the British instituted in India is still
continuing today
it has never been the system has never
been reformed
so the bunch of people who are to whom
power was handed in 1947 they continued
the same system and it's it's such a
large country that any major change will
take a long time to percolate down to
the Grassroots level which is why you
know most likely that's why the current
government is
is not willing to do it right now it's
it's something that is maybe being
pushed down the line to a later time
maybe we'll do it later we have bigger
problems to to solve right now so that
is the reason why these narratives have
been pushed for such a long time and
they are still pushed right now the
Indian textbooks still lie to students
they still serve the purpose of
brainwashing students and make them hate
their own religion and culture and
ancestors in the process
excuse me
says
I came across some outrageous claims on
the internet that Buddhist monks were
persecuted by brahmanas in Ancient India
and brahmanas were solely responsible
for the downfall of Buddhism in India
please shed some light on this topic see
this is part of the same narrative that
we were just speaking about Buddhist
monks being persecuted by brahmanas
do we understand the the nature of power
I think it was
eloquently stated
and gave the The Secret of what power is
he said that political power flows out
of the barrel of a gun
a gun
power only comes with the the the
possibility of violence
you know if you it's about it's kind of
like what Marxism says you know if you
can control the means of production then
you can control the whole country so
when it comes to power if you can
control the elements that can
elements of violence then you have power
so power you don't come to
so imagine a democratic election in
which somebody is elected and becomes
the prime minister or president that is
simply a title do they actually have
power no they would not have it
immediately you have to build the power
and you have to actually gain control of
the Armed Forces the police and the true
instruments of power which are the
instruments of violence that's what
power is now if you want to persecute
somebody
you need to have control of the means of
violence did the brahmins have any
control of the means of violence in
India
did the brahmins have the authority to
order the the Kings to do this or to do
that it was the kings of India the
chatriyas who had the control of the
means of violence
power political power
flows out of the barrel of a gun and
from the blade of a sword
so political power was always held in
India by the chatriyas or the rajputs
they were later called rajputs you know
these ruling the ancient aristocratic
Clan the post Rigby Clans posed by the
Clans so
political power was always held by the
chatriyas known by the brahmins the job
of the brahmins their Duty was to
was to preserve and inculcate India's
ancient knowledge and wisdom they were
the teachers they never had any
political power they never had any
control of the Armed Forces so in what
sense can they unleash persecution on
anyone
think logically
think logically always go down to First
principles if you want to persecute
somebody you need to have control of the
means of violence persecution is always
it is always a violent thing
and to enforce violence you read the
means of violence
the armed forces the police forces
the the state Machinery the bureaucracy
the governance machinery and all of
these things were historically always
in the hands of the
ruling class in India which were always
the qatarias
so in what sense does it make any sense
for the brahmanas to be in a position to
to persecute anyone
so this is a lie that brahmins
persecuted Buddhists monks or whatever
and brahmanas were responsible for the
downfall of Buddhism in India it was
that Turks who were responsible for the
downfall of Buddhism in India
there was a whole Buddhist built in
Northern India and Eastern India and
Western India from Gandhara and and all
the way from uh
the the border with Iran
all the way to the east
to to sword nabumi which is a Myanmar in
Thailand and all that so and you had the
great Buddhist mahaviharas uh and
various great universities in India like
Etc in Orlando they taught The Vedas
they also taught the precepts of
Buddhism it was not simply a Buddhist
Monastery or a Buddhist University
uh a lot of what we believed with
Buddhism Buddhist elements were actually
Hindu elements for instance they said
that the kushan Emperors were Buddhist
Emperors look at the coinage of the
greatest emperor kanishka
only five percent of his coins show
Buddhist uh themes 95 show other gods
and still they claim you know the
Buddhist King so the point is Buddhism
was eradicated by the Turks
they called you know what they call
Idols booth what does booth mean it
means Buddha they eradicated the Turks
eradicated Buddhism from the entirety of
Central Asia the whole of Central Asia
was Buddhist
everything was wiped out then it started
with gandar
which is present-day Afghanistan you
will find ruins of monasteries all
across Afghanistan Miss inak is is an
excellent example which is now under
threat because of the copper which is
found in the region
so the Turks destroyed they even wrote
poems about destroying Buddhist statues
the statues of Buddhas you will hardly
find a single statue of the Buddha in
India which doesn't which is still has
has its heads head on its shoulders
it was all done by the Turks
not by the brahmins so what you do is
you first and India's intellectual
historians Etc what they do is they take
all the crimes and atrocities populated
by the Turks in India and they ascribe
it to the brahmins and they raise
inter-generations of Indians who hate
their own culture as a consequence of
this
so once again the objective is to
make Indians hate their own culture and
religion and their own ancestry
and to
to facilitate the conversion of the
entire population of India out of
dharmic faiths
and you know the the Japanese were very
clear about this the samurai is
they so they they wrote about this okay
I'm not making this claim they made this
claim they wrote that when a Japanese
person converts to Christianity they
become International and that's why they
persecuted they tried they opposed
Christianity violently the samurai is
that's what they wrote
so if there is any truth to that if
there is I'm not sure if there is but if
there is then such uh then you know
so that could be the objective
to to make India more open and amenable
to foreign
influence so that they can create an
enormous captive audience in India
for their
products convert India into a captive
market and leech and drain all the value
all the money out of India all the
resources this is called
neocolonialization so all of this is
facilitated by the education system and
the so-called intellectuals and
historians who take all the atrocities
and crimes perpetrated by the Turks and
ascribe them
to the brahmins
and most Indians believe this nonsense
that's the problem that's a tragedy
per DD says can you explain why the
Indian education system is a failure but
it still produced many great people
can you give your opinions excuse me
look
India has produced many great people no
doubt about it
but
how many of them have been produced by
the education system and how many of
them have become great despite the
education system is what we have to ask
ourselves
take the example of srinivas ramanujan
one of the greatest mathematicians of
all time
did the Indian education system produce
him
no
the Indian education almost destroyed
him
he excelled at mathematics but he was he
was very poor in his studies when it
came to English grammar and social
studies or whatever else it was
and there was a there was the chance
that he would not be allowed to to pass
the tensored exam or whatever it was the
education system did its best to destroy
him
he got lucky that's why he's known to
the world I can assure you there are
many more ramanujans who have come and
gone and the world has never come come
to know of them because the education
system destroyed them so if somebody
somehow succeeds in India it's despite
the education system not because of the
education system
let me give you the example of there are
so many great institutions in India
educational institutions in India there
is something called the incident of
advanced studies or something in shimna
Shimla there are so many so-called great
universities of in India there are so
many iits in India tell me something
what great ground
breaking work
have they done in the past 20 years 50
years produce what tell me a single
great achievement that has been produced
by the Indian Institute of of advanced
study Shimla or by IIT whatever which is
whichever is your favorite IIT or
whichever is your favorite University
tell me one result they have produced
which is world class in nature
top of the best best of the best nothing
the Indian educational institutes are
institutions that that produce
mediocrity I'm not saying all the uh
professors and teachers therein are
mediocre maybe two percent or three
percent are exceptional but they have to
work within the horrible mediocre system
that that prioritizes mediocrity and
punishes greatness or brilliance
so if if we do produce some great
scientists
like Professor Desi Raju Etc it is that
the fact is that they have excelled
despite the system not because of the
system the Indian education system is
designed
to seek out and Destroy Talent
and to promote and reward mediocrity
that is the true nature of the Indian
education system and it considers
the academic staff and non-academic
staff to be the true stakeholders it
considers the students to be a nuisance
ask yourself a simple question
let's say a student misbehaves in class
what's going to happen that student is
most likely going to be going to be
suspended or thrown out
of the educational institution the
school the college the university very
high chance the student will be
punished harshly and thrown out imagine
a staff member misbehaves in the same
manner most likely it will be hushed up
and nothing will happen
maybe some technical punishment will be
given you know suspension for a week at
worst or something like that and then
they are back and nothing is it it says
if nothing happened
so
it it the education system treats the
stuff
as the stakeholders not the students
the actual purpose of an education
system is to treat the stakeholder the
students as stakeholders
it's its job is to produce confident
highly capable young adults who are
capable of taking on the world and
changing the world that's not what the
Indian education system does it produces
diffident
insecure
uh young adults who are clueless and
confused and who don't have any real
skills
so you you come with a degree in
whatever and then you have to go and get
a job and then you have to be trained
all over again when you start the job
that's what happens so the engineered
education system is a complete failure
it does not produce any great people
whatever great people India's produce
have have been produced despite the
education system they have had to fight
the education system every step of the
way and then get out of it and then
succeed somehow in life that's what's
happened don't describe any greatness in
India to the education system that's not
the case
next question Sangeeta says people say a
good people say good educated people
should be the country's head but Prime
Minister Modi has not any higher
educational degree don't you think we
choose we chose a wrong leader for our
country who is not enough educated do
you not think there should be a law
introduced for minimum educational
qualifications
that should be required to become an MP
or MLA in our country and what our
thoughts on PM modi's leadership all
those things ah so as far as I know
Prime Minister Modi has a master's
degree in something or the other
so he does a master's degree
uh so should the country's leader be a
highly educated person we had such a
person
Dr Manmohan Singh extremely Highly
Educated person with a PhD
how was his leadership
by any objective measure
of the output of his government the
achievements of his government he was in
power for 10 years
what achievements
did his government can his government
government boost of in 10 years
he was an extremely well educated person
today we are prime minister who has a
master's degree less supposedly less
educated than Dr Manmohan Singh
and the question is should we have
a law that we need to have a certain
minimum amount of education
qualifications if you want to become MP
or MLA I think education the education
does not tell you anything
about a person's capabilities
firstly this applies to not just the
Indian education system but to any
education system in the world
a person may be brilliant
even if they have not acquired a high
degree
uh you know in politics and Leadership
what matters your understanding of the
country and its people and their
problems
and your ability
to solve those problems by using other
people in these Machinery of the
governance system that you have that's
what matters in in leadership
do you think the great imagine all the
great leaders of our times or in in past
history
how many of them have been highly
educated
what was Alexander the Great's
educational degree
what about Julius Caesar what about
Hannibal Barca what about changes Khan
was highly educated true
so
and and I think he stood first in the
Indian civil services which is now
called the IAS so he's an exception
but most of the greatest leaders of all
time did not have any great educational
degree so there is no correspondence or
correlation between the high between a
high between being highly educated and
being a great leader
or being a great politician there is no
actual correspondence
and when it comes to the Indian
education system like like I said it
promotes mediocrity destroys Talent
to the people who come out on top are
the most mediocre people actually
you will see that people who uh you know
stand in the top 10 or their top 100 in
your 10th standard exam or personality
exam or whatever
wait for 20 30 years and see what they
achieve in life it's typically the
people who are in the middle benches or
the last benches who will become the
best business people the best
entrepreneurs or maybe the best
politicians
and the ones who get the highest marks
typically end up doing nine to five jobs
and being very good employees
because the the education system teaches
you to conform
obey and confirm so the most successful
ones are the most mediocre who obey the
best
it is the rebels who don't do well in
the education system who actually can
change the world
so I think it's a very bad idea to have
any law like this that you need a
certain minimum education qualification
which is the complete waste of time
actually I think once you're done with
the 12 Summit exam should be should be
out in the world and unless you you are
you you you
want to be a great scientist or or you
know if you have certain a certain kind
of aptitude or inclination then you can
go and pursue higher education but
overall it really adds nothing much to
your life
so most people they just want to go and
work right
so I think it makes sense that once
you're 16 17 you should be out in the in
the world and become an apprentice in
some some industry and start learning on
the job itself that makes much more
sense and even in politics you can
become if you want to be a leader or a
politician mpmla become politically
active in some political party the youth
Wing or whatever it is whichever your
favorite political party is by the time
you're 17 18. you don't need high
education to be a better politician or a
better leader
so
so I don't agree at all
that that we need Highly Educated people
or we need to have a bar that people
must cross in terms of educational
qualifications before they are allowed
allowed to become MPS or mlas that's
that's a very bad idea
and uh do we do I think we have chosen a
wrong leader for our country I mean look
at how India has changed in the past
seven eight years
the most educated people who were Prime
Ministers before Mr Modi what did they
achieve he has achieved more in the past
seven eight years than most of them have
achieved in the past 70 years
like we just spoke of a while ago it is
now for the first time after India's
Independence that the world takes India
seriously and when India does something
they they take notice and they listen
it's only happened in the past seven
eight years it's not thanks to Mr
Manmohan Singh or anybody else this has
happened so I don't think
that educational qualifications make any
difference in leadership a genuinely
great leader is somebody who understands
the people the nation the potential that
the nation has the problems the nation
is facing and that leader also has the
ability to find Solutions and to get
people on board the message and and
and the direction in which the nation
needs to go these are the qualities of a
great leader and that doesn't come with
education you can take a theoretical
course in leadership or political
science it's gonna give you no real real
world skills
you'll be filled with bookish knowledge
you know when you want to become a
genuine
let's say physicist or mathematician the
way to do it is to solve problems not by
reading books you can sit all day and
read textbooks it's going to give you no
actual skills the only skills your Gail
will be gained when you actually take a
pen and paper and start solving problems
similarly when it comes to political
science and Leadership you can take
courses and read books it will teach you
nothing it's only when you try to solve
problems which is means you go out in
society and try solving actual problems
that's when you develop leadership
skills
so I don't think educational degrees
matter at all in leadership and politics
and we should not have any such law that
says that we must have a certain minimum
qualification education qualification
without which you can't become MP or MLA
that's a very bad idea
oh excuse me
jp112 says
excuse me
a big fan from Bangladesh thank you very
much so thank you
can the Indian subcontinent reunite
again and work like the EU what should
be the steps and how much time will it
take
you know historically Indian history has
gone through Cycles it's a cyclical
process
there have been times of political
unification of the entire subcontinent
when you had great
Emperors leaders of India
the mauryan Empire it it reached its
Pinnacle under Emperor Ashok the Great
the kushan Empire it reached its
Pinnacle under uh
Emperor kanishka the great so you had
great Emperors like uh Ashoka
chandragupta also kanishka you had the
Chola Emperors you had uh the Kota
Dynasty and so on there have been times
when India has been politically United
as as an entire subcontinent under one
Empire but there have been times in
between which are more frequent when
India has been politically disunited
lots of small the guptas I forgot to
mention the Gupta Empire as well but
there have been times when India has
been disunited not under a single
political leadership lots of different
kingdoms small medium largest kingdoms
here and there
and different dominions
so
in during those times where India was
not under a single Empire in those times
India did function like what the EU
functions like today
of course in the EU you have a president
of the EU and the central leadership in
Brussels and all that uh that was not
there
but you had essentially opened borders
in India you did not need passports and
visas to apply to travel from one
Kingdom to another you do not have that
and you had the same civilizational
language which typically was Sanskrit
and you had the same culture
so you may come from let's say uh let's
say magadh and let's say you want to go
uh to the to somewhere in in Southern
India
there will be a common language that
everybody understands which will be
Sanskrit and you all practice the same
essentially the same culture Hinduism in
its various forms but you understand
what it's all about so there will be no
cultural shock there will be a language
shock or whatever a little bit but you
all speak Sanskrit as the common
language so it was the EU kind of system
whenever India was disuniented you had
lots of Kingdoms the common civilians
Etc they could go from Kingdom to
Kingdom for trade or whatever and there
was no
no problem as such so it was very much a
eu-like system apart from the central
leadership that EU is supposed to have
uh today we have the westphalian nation
state system which means that you need
to have these passports and visas to
travel from one nation to another India
and Nepal don't have this as a system
which is a good thing uh so imagine a
system which has the India Nepal kind of
arrangement all over so when it comes to
India Sri Lanka also no passport no Visa
needed just show your documents and get
in no no authorization needed that could
happen when it comes to Nations like
Bangladesh Afghanistan Pakistan it's
still problematic
when it comes to Bangladesh whether you
like it or not there is the problem of
illegal immigration immigration into
India which is a huge major problem and
I don't think there's any long-term
solution now except for eventually
creating eu-like system or maybe
reabsorbing Bangladesh into India in the
free distance future perhaps
when well it starts that can happen
anytime in the immediate future
uh
it's possible that this sort of thing
could happen again so what steps need to
be taken first of all Pakistan is a
problem
there's a reason why sarc doesn't work
the South Asian corporate
uh South Asian whatever for regional
cooperation that system that
organization it is no longer functional
because of Pakistan the terrorist Nation
the first problem that stands in the way
of EU like system in a in the
subcontinent is Pakistan Pakistan is a
terrorist Nation it is a proxy for other
nations to destabilize the subcontinent
all of us it's a problem for Afghanistan
it's a problem for Iran and of course
it's a problem for India the first thing
needs that needs to happen is that the
Pakistani army needs to be neutralized
it is holding the entire population of
Pakistan hostage
and leeching off them taking out all the
value from Pakistan and stashing it into
foreign bank accounts and when these
generals and politicians retire they
they go and live in other countries and
that typically the children are citizens
of other countries and enjoy the great
life there in the west so the Pakistani
army needs to be neutralized it needs to
be dealt with it's a terrorist
organization it's a mercenary
organization it is not working for
the interest of the people of Pakistan
or the interest of the people of the
subcontinent
so once the Pakistani army is dealt with
it's gonna end up in the fragmentation
of Pakistan into four pieces I would say
Sindhu Desh Punjab uh
most likely would want to be
reintegrated itself with Afghanistan
which which makes sense
will be reabsorbed by India where it
they belong actually
uh so once that happens it's gonna we
still can't have a EU like system where
people can travel freely because the
population of Pakistan is deeply
radicalized they've been taught since
day one that India is the enemy
and it's a cultural thing issue cultural
issue as well religious issue as well
they hate everybody who doesn't uh
follow their religion
so even after Pakistan
is dealt with in this manner peacefully
hopefully uh we will not be able to have
immediately you like system where people
can start traveling freely because
that's gonna create huge problems for
India so there needs to be a period of
deer radicalization which will take
several Generations maybe 30 40 50 60
years maybe a century
maybe a century it's a long-term process
it's not going to happen next week my
friends
and similarly with Bangladesh also there
are these very strong anti-india
sentiments in significant numbers of
Bangladeshi people whether you like it
or not it's the truth
just when was Bangladesh liberated from
Pakistan 71 that's about 40 years ago in
just 40 years they've become extremely
strongly Pro Pakistan despite everything
Pakistan did to their ancestors
and their own people
many bangladeshis are strongly
pro-pakistan and anti-india so we can't
have an open border with Bangladesh the
way we have with Nepal under those
circumstances
um
it's gonna take time so maybe 50 years
or so
and when the the populations of these
nations are significantly de radicalized
and they no longer hate everybody else
in the subcontinent
then we can open up the borders possibly
and have a eu-like system in the
subcontinent which would I would expect
it to
include Afghanistan Pakistan uh
Bangladesh Nepal Sri Lanka Maldives
possibly Burma also possibly if they
want to but that's not going to happen
anytime in the near future at least 50
years will have to pass and only if
certain measures are taken can this
happen
so it's it's a distant dream for now for
now it's a distant dream
cast says we all know how Europeans took
over the entirety of the American
continent by con conducting barbaric
genocide against the Native Americans
but did Europeans conduct any genocide
against the Africans African people map
where's the map
all right map
here is the map so we know that uh which
year was it 1492 was it that that uh
Columbus discovered discovered America
so for about 500 years these people have
been uh
have been conducting their colonization
of various parts of the world they took
over uh North and South America they
took over Australia and Tasmania New
Zealand and Africa so there are two
kinds of colonialism colonization one is
settler colonization and the other one
is economic colonization in settler
colonization you take over an entire
region and eradicate the natives from
that region or subjugate them and reduce
them to third class status
and then you take over the entire land
and you take the best part of the land
and you create your own Citizen and
countries on it that's what happened in
North America and South America the
natives don't figure anywhere in the in
the politics or the leadership or the
administration or anything in these
regions Canada the US Mexico in Canada
and the US the national language is
English the governance system is the
essentially an outgrowth of the British
governance system in Southern America in
Brazil it's Portuguese in the other
countries it is Spanish in Central
America again it's Spanish
so these nations these regions have
suffered from settler colonization and
especially in North America there was a
horrific genocide conducted by the
Europeans of the Native Americans
approximately a hundred million Native
Americans were killed off which is a
shocking horrific number
and today they talk about human rights
and democracy
uh so yes there was a like like rodrigit
says this barbaric genocide of the
Native Americans in Australia the same
thing happened even today the natives of
Australia the so-called aboriginals are
second-class citizens in Australia they
are made to live in the harsh Hinterland
the the internal lands of Australia
while all the green regions the coastal
regions have been taken over by the
Invaders the descendants of the
colonialists
in Tasmania the native tasmanians were
entirely exterminated not a single one
of them is alive today in New Zealand
again the maoris are are essentially to
a significant extent treated like
certain second-class citizens
the rate of crime of drug abuse of
alcoholism suicide Etc is very high
among the natives compared to the uh
descendants of the colonizers
so we know all this happened when it
comes to Africa the Europeans did not
indulge in settler colonialism except
for places like South Africa Namibia uh
Etc in other parts of Africa they only
indulged in
resource colonization colonialism and
economic colonization
but there were genocides in Africa as
well the best example is the Congo
genocide conducted by the belgians
so today the EU Capital Brussels is in
Belgium yes they talk about human rights
and democracy well they are the
perpetrators the billions of one of the
worst genocides in human history at
least 10 million uh Congolese
persons people were massacred
over a period of about 30 years or so by
the belgians under the great king
Leopold
and the entire region was totally
devastated and impoverished people were
made to work on these rubber plantations
and other plantations and they had they
were given quotas of how much produce
product to uh give back to the Masters
every day and if they did not meet the
quotas their hands and legs were cut off
including the hands and legs of small
children that's the horrific
abuses and atrocities the belgians
perpetrated in Congo and today they talk
about human rights
so yes and obviously there were many
more genocides
the Germans colonized part of parts of
Africa they also wiped out entire
ethnicities of people you know tens of
thousands maybe hundreds of thousands of
people so it's an Untold Story
there is so much that's happened to
Africa that nobody writes about and
nobody wants to speak about then
unfortunately Africa is still being
colonized economically by various
European nations today not just European
nations but also by other nations today
has spoken about this she is a big fan
of Mr macaw
so yeah it's still going on
so yes the Europeans did conduct
genocides against the Africans
shivansh says why are black of Americans
called African-Americans but white
Americans are called are not called
European Americans excellent questions
anybody who has any African ancestry is
called earlier they were called blacks
earlier they used much worse words for
the for the African uh
Americans which I will not repeat here
they were also called blacks I think
they're still called black people but
nowadays they're called people of some
some of them are called
another term is is person of color which
applies to even brown-skinned people
like us and uh nowadays the the correct
terminology is African-American
and they have this one drop rule in the
U.S which means if a person has even one
drop of African blood they are
considered to be black or
African-American which is weird
another question is why are white
Americans not called European Americans
when black people are called
African-Americans it's very strange some
white people do identify as as Irish
American or Italian-American which means
they see you Europe not as a monolithic
entity but as a very diverse region full
of
uh sub-ethnicities
so in the western mind in their
worldview Europe is a region which is as
we can see it's much smaller than Africa
much smaller
but it's a very diverse place so it's
not right to call anybody a European
American you're either Italian-American
or Irish American or French American or
German American but not European
American but the Western mind sees
Africa this enormous continent is a
single monolithic entity
so every anybody who comes from Africa
who has ancestry in Africa is
African-American as if Africa is just
one monolithic single ethnic group which
is not the case
if you if you ask recent Americans or
recent immigrants from Africa or America
they will identify as Ethiopian American
or nigerian-american or or whatever
Tanzanian American Congo is American the
Somalian American but for the
non-africans they are all the same
so the white people the the Europeans
they see Africa as a single entity as a
monolithic entity they don't recognize
the fact that there are hundreds of
ethnic groups and hundreds of cultures
within Africa the genetic and ethnic and
cultural diversity in Africa X far
exceeds far surpasses anything seen
anywhere else in the world that's how
diverse Africa is so you go to Africa
you go to Egypt they will not see the
themselves as the same ethnicity as
somebody in Niger or or Sierra Leone or
or or Kenya the Egyptians don't see
themselves as the same as those people
they are a different ethnicity in
different culture in the same ways for
goes for people in Tanzania and Kenya in
Ethiopia in Eritrea in Namibia in in
Gabon
they all see themselves as distinct
ethnicities with very distinct
Traditions very distinct uh Heritage and
culture and way of life
so we have to understand that Africa is
an extremely diverse place but the
Europeans the the westerners don't see
it that way they want to see
oversimplify everything
and it is an insult to Africa that any
black person is simply called an
African-American rather than trying to
go into the roots and the other reason
is that the Americans simply don't care
and there is no way of knowing today
what the roots of many of these African
Americans are many of them were brought
in as slaves from Western Africa but no
one knew which specific ethnic group
they came from in over time they they
themselves forgot what their place of
origin was or after several Generations
because they were treated as slaves then
children would be uprooted from their
parents and sold off somewhere else and
they would never see their parents again
so they would not have any shared
history that was passed down from parent
to child it's horrific what has been
done to the African Americans
and that's why they only see them from
South Africa anymore today most of them
don't know
what their original ethnicity was what
their original culture was where their
ancestors were kidnapped from and
brought to America as slaves we know it
typically happened from Western Africa
but there are many nations from inside
Africa from where these slaves were
procured
uh it's it's a it's a terrible terrible
history and it's it's sad what has been
done to Africa
so that's the reason why black Americans
are typically just called African
Americans but newer immigrants to
America from Africa they will see
themselves and they will identified not
as African-American but as whatever
region it is you know Nigerian American
or or Senegalese American or Congolese
American
arcanian American or Ethiopian American
or whatever else
says why didn't the Ottomans conquer and
occupy Persia even after defeating
Persia numerous times
so uh okay let's look at the map we
should see the map to understand uh what
this is about
right so Persia is Iran what we now call
Iran is a historically built Persia
and the Ottoman Empire was centered
around Turkey the capital was
Constantinople now called Istanbul
and the Ottoman Empire
it expanded northwards and westwards and
to some extent eastwards as well uh Iraq
Syria Jordan all of that was part of the
Ottoman Empire so was the Arabian
Peninsula also Egypt and some parts of
North Africa at the time
and in the west they had the safavids
the the portions uh and these were two
powerful entities and they did go to war
several times there was the Battle of
chaldiran the battle of dim dim the
Battle of Baghdad in this in the 17th
century significant battles
uh and and the Ottomans captured Baghdad
from the Persians and that's how Iraq
came into
ottoman hands in the 17th century there
was a major blow to the person safavid
Empire so these two uh Empires had a
common boundary which made them
adversaries
but typically what happened is that uh
the see Persia was to to some extent
it's a very large geographical region
it's definitely much smaller than India
but it is still a very large
uh
country or geographical region it is
much larger than present-day turkey and
their empire the Persian Empire also was
larger than what it was it went beyond
the present day boundaries of Iran
so these were two significant Empires
and it did not make sense most likely
for the Ottomans to try and
conquer the Persian Heartland because
they would meet enormous resistance
there the Persian Empire was a
well-oiled Empire well organized Empire
it had this great history of of fighting
of Invaders and
it was so so it it could not be
conquered easily it would cost a great
amount of of resources which may be
those resources could could be used
Elsewhere for the Ottoman Empire so the
size and the strength of Persia firstly
was the major reason why the Ottomans
never tried very seriously to conquer
Persia they did conquer you know parts
of the Persian Empire which were
non-persian regions like Iraq for
instance obviously like I said in the
17th century the Battle of Baghdad they
captured Baghdad and after that it
became part of the Ottoman Empire but
they never tried to capture seriously
Persia itself because that would be
too difficult most likely secondly it's
a religious thing the Shia Sunni issue
the Ottoman Empire was a Sunni Empire
Persia was a Shia country a Shia uh
Empire and if they went to war with the
shias the Ottomans also had various Shia
sects and ethnic and ethics ethnic
groups within their empire they possibly
did not want to
to set off a Shia Sunni kind of conflict
within their own Empire by trying to
invade Persia so that is a possibility
uh and they also had reasonably good uh
diplomatic and political relations with
the Persians so that could also
contribute to that so mainly their focus
was westwards for the Ottomans
it was westwards they wanted to conquer
Europe I think they say the Ottomans the
Turks they started off as Central Asian
Nomads they conquered Anatolia and they
they had this practice of bride
capturing and there were so many
helpless defenseless families in
Anatolia All Greek origin people some
Armenian some Georgian Etc so they
they would kidnap these women and force
them to marry and convert to the
religion and that's how the entire
ethnicity of the Turks changed today
they looked just like Europeans
mainly the the overall are more or less
the same as the Greeks the ethnicity is
more of a thing the same if you do
genetic analysis you will see that the
paternal haplogroups are Central Asian
haplogroups the lineages but the
matrilineal lineages are all local Greek
and Armenian and all that so
over time they they became European in
appearance and maybe they identified
more with Europe than with Asia so the
Persians obviously are not Europeans the
Persians are not white people uh
so maybe some of that may also have
played a factor that they identified
more with Europe and they wanted to
conquer Europe uh you know
the Byzantine Empire that they conquered
was the Eastern Roman Empire and some of
their Emperors did Express the desire to
conquer Western Rome as well so that
their focus historically was always best
words and their major threats were also
West was the Christian nations
so uh so given the choice I think they
wanted to fight the Christians more than
their fellow Muslims even though they
were sunnis so it's a combination of
these factors that
that uh caused the the Ottomans
to not take the possibility of
conquering Persia seriously and they
always Focus their energies and their
conquests westwards even though they did
fight a few Wars with the Persians and
they did take some territory from the
Persians but overall it was just too
much of a stretch too big of an ask for
them
amazing Indian citizen says many
Travelers have written that in Ancient
India theft was so low that many people
kept their doors and windows open but
then how did they prevent mosquitoes and
other insects from coming into the house
excuse me
good question uh
yeah
so theft was very low and the crime was
very low so most Indians kept their
doors and windows open at night and
slept with the doors and windows open in
villages and towns all that the problem
is that India is
a very uh warm Nation warm climate very
healthy climate lots of rivers lots of
water bodies lakes and all that
especially historically every village
would have at least a pond or a lake now
it's no longer the case but historically
it was like that so
that obviously has it creates this
problem of mosquito breeding so
mosquitoes must have been a problem in
Asia India so what did Indians do we had
a practice called fumigation ayurvedic
fumigation so what they would do is they
would take a big bowel kind of thing you
know big huge bowel in which they would
uh put dried cow dung and various uh
herbs dried out herbal uh components
that would ward off insects and
mosquitoes and there is a practice many
Indians even practice in the 20th
century
especially in villages and all that so
big bow like instrument or or or vessel
in which you you put cow dung and maybe
some hay maybe some chips of wood and
these ayurvedic plants dried out plants
or whatever that would keep on burning
slowly throughout the night give off
smoke that would not be harmful to
humans but it would ward off insects
especially mosquitoes you put that in a
corner of the room in the house there
were no fan ceiling fans at the time so
it'll just keep on burning slowly
the smoke will permeate the house maybe
give a nice smell as well it would not
harm humans whatsoever but it would keep
mosquitoes away so all this knowledge
was encoded in ayurveda
we have kind of lost all those things
today today we use chemicals
those sprays and all that to ward of
insects and mosquitoes uh we also have
those those spiral Spiral things right
that you burn in this they keep burning
through the night so that comes from the
ancient practice that Indians had of
fumigating the house uh typically would
fumigate it once a week or once a month
properly keep get everybody out of the
house and put a big blast of smoke that
will keep kill off any insects that have
been hidden somewhere but typically you
would do that every night to a lesser
degree and that's how Indians in old
days warded of mosquitoes and other
insects interesting question that you
asked here
Daniel Nicholson says with present day
technology is it possible to genetically
re-engineer extinct species like
dinosaurs sabertooths and mammoths how
long can DNA be used to clone life
because before it becomes useless
a good question so uh
uh technically it can be done if you
have the source DNA of the extinct
species then you can use that to
recreate you know to clone that ancient
species
and create a
and to bring it back to life but when it
comes to dinosaurs dinosaurs
the non-avian dinosaurs died out about
66 million years ago the avian ones are
still around they're all around us in
case you don't know so when it comes to
let's say you want to to uh re-engineer
the extinct Tyrannosaurus Rex species of
dinosaurs then first of all you would
need a screen you would need the
original DNA the code the genetic
blueprint of the T-Rex do we have it we
don't have it so DNA degrades over time
DNA is fragile it does it's quite Hardy
it's also fragile
so you can extract DNA from ancient
humans who died let's say 10 000 years
ago you can extract DNA from animals
that died 20 30 000 years ago but when
it comes to animals that died millions
of years ago it's very hard to extract
DNA from The Remains first of all the
remains are fossilized typically of
course one it has been discovered that
many T-Rex fossils when you break the
femur which is the thigh bone there
still is often soft tissue wet tissue
inside and they have discovered tissue
that contains blood vessels and even
what looks like rbc's red blood cells so
it may perhaps be possible to extract
some DNA I don't think it's been done
thus far at least nobody is publishing
any research paper
saying that it's been done but the
possibility does exist
but if you do extract DNA that DNA is
going to be degraded and damaged which
means it will have missing sequences
then how do you re-engineer the species
one thing you could do is you take the
the DNA of a closely related animal like
the chicken for instance or the turkey
and you take the DNA of the turkey and
you use that to fill in the missing gaps
in the DNA of the or the T-Rex and then
you
try to implant that into
you know and maybe hatch an egg you
think you take uh
you take a fertilized
or unfertilized chicken egg or perhaps
turkey egg and you fertilize it with a
sperm which contains the modified DNA
and then hopefully it will give rise to
a T-Rex that's that's theoretically how
you would do it when it comes to
mammoths for instance mammals went
extinct about 10 000 years ago and we
find a well-preserved frozen mammoth
bodies in the permafrost in Siberia Etc
quite frequently so we do have access to
Mammoth DNA mostly undamaged Mammoth DNA
so what you could do is you take a very
closely related species like the Indian
elephant for instance which I think is
the closest relative to the extinct
mammoth
then you simply insert Mammoth DNA into
um and and uh you create you create an
embryo and a fetus out of it and then
you implant that into the womb of a
female Indian elephant and after
whatever months it is she will give
birth to a next to to an actual Mammoth
that is something that can be done I'm
sure if we want to I'm not sure if
anybody has done it obviously it would
be big news if somebody did that but I
think that's much closer to Big reality
than dinosaurs uh sabertooths also it
may be possible you take uh
an animal of a similar size a kind of a
similar size like a puma or a Lynx or a
leopard or maybe a tiger or whatever and
you do the same procedure it will be
possible to give birth to an actual
saber tooth infant
so that's that's something that's closer
to reality then then to bring then
bringing back dinosaurs
uh so how long can DNA be used to clone
life before it becomes useless DNA which
is is in a dead organism's body it
degrades over time if it is well
preserved uh in a dry environment it may
last longer especially if the
environment is cool when it comes to
India the environment is hot warm
there's a lot of rainfall that's why any
buried body will degrade very fast and
it's very hard to extract viable DNA
from that that's why it's been so hard
to extract DNA from uh the Saraswati
Hindu region where you do find skeletons
but the DNA is typically highly degraded
uh
when it comes to uh
human bodies or animal bodies that are
frozen let's say in permafrost
then the DNA typically stays more or
less significantly more intact than it
would otherwise do so I would say that
maybe it would be possible to extract
viable DNA from a dead organism that is
maybe a few tens of thousand years old
but when it comes to the time scale of
millions of years it becomes extremely
difficult to extract any useful usable
genetic information
foreign
I want to know about hypnotism is it
real or is it just a trick I've seen
many people sharing their experience
about their past life hypnotized can a
human brain remember fragments of the
past life what are your thoughts on this
listen I have no idea about past lives I
can talk to you about what see there is
no actual scientific evidence of past
lives people have stories but you can't
prove those stories you can't
corroborate those stories scientifically
to actually prove uh reincarnation you
have to first prove the existence of the
soul the soul is a non-physical object
you can't measure it quantify it take
pictures of it weigh it so it is
something that is beyond the realm of
science then therefore the the entire
idea of rebirth reincarnation is beyond
the realm of science it belongs to the
realm of philosophy or psychology or or
yeah philosophy philosophy not science
so you cannot discuss it from a
scientific perspective what I talk about
is from a scientific perspective mainly
so I don't know about reincarnation past
life all those things the question is I
will take the question about hypnotism
what is hypnosis
so hip process is is a state a mental
state of heightened suggestibility
where an individual is more receptive to
external suggestions
then otherwise he or she would be and
based on these external suggestions that
person may exhibit and experience
changes in perception and behavior
so hypnosis is induced through a variety
of techniques you know standard
techniques relaxation techniques like
meat breathing you start with deep
breathing you relax the body progressive
muscle relaxation and then you there are
scripts hypnosis text scripts you read
out the script and the person has to
follow the procedure the orders and that
is what is used to guide the individual
the person into a deep hypnotic state
so it's it's been used for a variety of
purposes typically therapeutic purposes
to reduce somebody's anxiety to improve
the quality of a person's sleep uh to to
cure phobias you know to treat phobias
and to treat certain mental health
conditions and hypnosis is also used by
by these entertainers you know stage
hypnosis and all that where a hypnot
when a person a hypnotist will invite
volunteers from the audience to
participate in hypnosis experiments
which are typically entertaining funny
or bizarre or some of some kind so
that's what it process is it is not mind
control you cannot be hypnotized by
somebody against your will
you can only be hypnotized if you allow
them to hypnotize you nobody can
forcefully hypnotize you okay so people
cannot be forcefully hypnotized and they
cannot be forcefully made to do things
against their wishes and against their
belief or their or their ethics and
morality
and hypnosis may not be effective
with everybody so some people may be
more susceptible to hypnosis and some
people may be such that it is almost
impossible to hypnotize them even if
they want to be hypnotized
so that is what hypnosis is see they say
that the human mind the psyche has a
conscious element and a subconscious
element a subconscious mind in a
conscious mind so hypnosis is something
that typically opens up the subconscious
mind to active suggestion and
participation and you know you can even
hypnotize yourself
there are books and scripts available
that you have to follow and you can
actually hypnotize yourself
it's an interesting I'm sure you can
simply Google it self-hypnosis script
and obviously each self-hypnosis script
will have a certain purpose some of them
are about you know and it's a you also
get these audio files you know uh
somebody puts you into this relaxed
mindset
they give you instructions you have to
mentally follow the instructions to
relax yourself calm yourself close your
eyes and repeat whatever is after them
count back from 20 to 1 or whatever and
it's an entire script which you can
listen to or you can even read it out to
yourself with your eyes open and that
will place you into a state of hypnosis
and each of these scripts will have a
certain purpose for some people it's
about more self-confidence or whatever
some people it's about quitting smoking
or quitting whatever addiction they have
so there are hypnosis scripts that are
ready made and available and they all
serve a certain purpose
it's very interesting you should try it
out and some of them are just just for
experiencing the state of hypnosis so I
have seen books that deal with this
topic and I have seen various uh
mentalists or whatever who who sell
hypnosis scripts it's a very interesting
topic and I'm sure you can access such
scripts online if you just do a simple
Google search try it out and see how it
feels interesting
um
okay Daniel says could you please
enlighten us about the Andromeda galaxy
which that is said to have a
cannibalistic appetite for other
galaxies
how why does a Galaxy devour smaller
galaxies will our deer Milky Way
eventually be gobbled up by Andromeda
look uh
galaxies don't have personalities and
behavioral traits and and preferences
you know people talk about black holes
as big Rogue black holes and vacuum
cleaners no it's not like that black
holes galaxies all objects in the
universe follow the laws of physics they
don't have individual quirks and
personalities so the Andromeda galaxy
doesn't have any cannibalistic appetite
for Galaxies
it is part of the local group of
galaxies all the galaxies outside the
local group are moving away from us
but the galaxies within the local group
our local group of which the Milky Way
is apart these galaxies are coming
towards each other because the force of
gravity overcomes the expansion of the
universe within the local group so
Andromeda galaxy in the Milky Way are
coming towards each other because of the
force of gravity which can be which you
will find in any textbook of physics
Neutron in derivative general relativity
that's all it is there is no special
Quirk that the Andromeda galaxy has that
it prefers to eat galaxies
so that's number one so yes endometer is
coming towards the Milky Way Milky Way
is going towards Andromeda they're
moving towards each other Andromeda is
larger than our galaxy eventually in
about 5 billion years or so roughly the
two galaxies will come together and
merge it's not going to be a collision
there will be nothing banging against
each other nothing
galaxies are mainly empty space
so the two galaxies will come together
merge and then Stars will be thrown out
in all directions it's going to be a
messy Affair for a long long time and
then eventually everything will will
come back together and they will merge
and form a much larger Galaxy and some
people give the name Milko Media or
whatever to it
So eventually that's what's going to
happen this process will begin in about
five billion years when the two galaxies
will come together and merge and the
merger will begin it's going to be a
galactic dance mediated by the force of
gravity mainly gravity only
and eventually you will have a much
larger composite Galaxy that emerges out
of that and most likely the black hole
at the supermassive black hole at the
center of the Andromeda galaxy and the
one at the center of our galaxy they
eventually will do a Tango they will go
around each other and eventually they
will merge too and that could give us a
give of spectacular fireworks that may
or may not be harmful to life in the
Galaxy if it does exist
that's what's going to happen my friends
okay I as always I have many more
questions which I will not have the time
to take let's take some questions from
the live chat do you all have any
questions
if you have questions please ask me and
I shall take a few
Mac Pro says the sun will not last that
long
uh the Sun
what will happen to the sun is
interesting so the Sun is going to
become a red giant
in about five billion years time so yes
by the time the the merger of Andromeda
and and the Milky Way happen the sun
will be more or less on its last legs
and eventually it's gonna give off its
its outer layers and and that which will
give rise to what we call a planetary
nebula and what will be left of the Sun
is going to be a white dwarf which
eventually will slowly slowly slowly
lose its its temperature and eventually
it will become a giant Diamond carbon
black dwarf eventually in the Far Far
Future
all right any other question let's see
I'm sure there are lots of other
questions
says what do you think please about good
relationship of a woman and built on
trust or love what with a woman any
relation is built on trust and love
when it comes to a relationship between
a man and woman it's it's has to be
built on trust and on love both things
you also need to have some common
objectives in life
so if your common objectives
match with
the the partners common common
objectives then you have a convergence
of geopolitical interests which means
that you can have a long-term
partnership that's how it typically
works
you see so it has to be built on trust
shared objectives shared interests and
love
without that it won't last long
okay uh
AJ ready is a new member welcome sir
thank you so much
time for my Discord server maybe I
should explore that option here I will
have to hire some people to do that
because last time I was trying to do it
myself and I didn't have the time to
administer it and some people were
trying to take over or whatever so maybe
in the future I should perhaps do that
again
uh
do we have any other interesting
questions
uh
what is the best way says somya to
inculcate self-discipline get rid of bad
addictions
well everybody has some bad habits on
the other everybody I'm sure has the
best way to indulcate self-discipline
you take one activity and focus on that
so the easiest example I can give you is
to join a gym and start lifting weights
and you've got to do it consistently you
give yourself a target of five or six
times a week you're gonna go to gym and
lift your weights you need to have a
program you lift weights and once you
become disciplined in that that
discipline is going to Premiere in other
sphere in your other spheres of life and
activity so if you become disciplined in
one activity in one aspect of your life
that discipline is like a muscle so it's
gonna you know spill over into other
aspects of your life as well when it
comes to bad addictions typically if you
are addicted to something let's say
smoking or drinking or whatever it is
hypothetically
you typically see it's it's an attempt
to fill some kind of Gap in your life
then the chemical dependency takes over
so it's really hard to I'm sure to to
get rid of these addictions
so typically what you have to do is you
have to replace that thing with
something that is better
so
Maybe
maybe get rid of the habit of Whatever
It Is by replacing it with something
else a healthier habit
so if you have a deduction to let's say
fast food you learn something new learn
a new skill cooking Cuisine and cook
something nice and healthy every day and
replace your fast food addiction with
your healthy eating and make that an
addiction so a healthy eating addiction
is going to be a good addiction right so
that that's typically what you have to
do it's obviously not as easy as a make
it sound over here it's really tough but
you gotta do that
all right I think I'm gonna end it over
here two hours ten minutes all right so
this is the end of today's session thank
you so much everybody for all the
questions and for participating and for
watching and we're gonna continue this
next week so I will see you in the next
week's live streams very soon not not
far away from me from today until then
take care
keep going raise your standards and I
will see you very soon thank you good
day good night bye